but you've mentioned it several times
now and frankly i'm not entirely clear
what you mean by it
so i'd love for you to take a five
minutes no longer i'm gonna blow the
whistle
on meaning what does meaning mean and
what is it to be
meaningful five minutes on
meaningfulness so
five minutes so i'm gonna start now i'm
gonna rely on old school skills and do a
compression
so first is uh in bed reference to john
verveigh's
you know 43 hour series on escaping from
the meaning crisis
go watch that you will then have a much
better sense of what that means
but to say john has a good framework so
i'll use that
as well as i can four ways of knowing
propositional
procedural perspectival participatory
and and they're in a stack which is to
say that participatory is more
fundamental
and propositional is um more
rapidly changeable you can you can move
propositions around faster propositions
like what we're doing right now language
i'm conveying language to you you're
absorbing language and to some extent
you're moving your ideas around
in relationship to what i'm saying
participatory
has to do with it's almost like the the
fitness
of your way of being in relationship to
the world that you're in so if you
actually use just evolutionary fitness
and extend that to include the whole way
that a human can be in relationship with
with the the kinds of niches that we
find ourselves in
that's where meaningfulness comes from
that is meaningfulness so meaningfulness
has to do with the
the wholeness of your entire mode of
being in the world
all the different ways that you respond
to what is coming at you
that gives rise to your increasing
capacity
to respond well to what is in the world
so meaningfulness is simultaneously the
means to the end
of being able to respond to the world in
a way that furthers your capacity to
respond to the world in the next moment
of time that you
you are fit in that sense um
and also it is the the capacity in
yourself
of how you sense what kinds of changes
in yourself
are more affordable to increasing that
capacity does that make sense
almost what exactly is the capacity
let's make that clear
the language i think of platinus talked
about the notion of conformation
to conform so there's a there's a
pistol let's do that i have a pistol in
front of me
it's a glock actually and so what i
notice is there's a way for my hand
to be configured so that my hand is
holding this glock in a way that is
actually able to pull the trigger
effectively does that make sense
yep that is a very large number of ways
that my hand can be conformed that isn't
in conformity with with the the
affordance of the pistol
so meaningfulness is simultaneously
on the one hand the practical which is
if i get my hand in the right conformity
to the pistol i can actually pull the
trigger and in fact if i get it
my whole body in the right relationship
with that with the affordance of the
pistol i can actually shoot with
accuracy
right so that's meaningfulness from the
point of view of effectiveness
in in world in relationship to what the
world is offering
and then there's the sense of
meaningfulness which is the how do i go
about figuring that [ __ ] out
well what i notice is that if i sort of
experiment with it there's something
about the way that i know i'm holding
the gun upside down if i've got like all
my fingers stuck together like a
mitt there's something in me that is
telling me that that ain't the right way
and so the sense of meaningfulness is
the capacity to be able to
discern in reality in this case with the
pistol
what are the affordances of that pistol
and how does my capacity as a body
relate to those affordances and how do i
change myself to conform to that
so as to increasingly realize a capacity
to
be an effective relationship with
reality now expand
pistol to be the whole [ __ ] world so
essentially you're saying is
uh meaning is figuring [ __ ] out
yes figuring out how to actually live in
life
well which is to say by well what i mean
is not just to live
now but to live ongoingly right it's
just this double order i have to be able
to
be in effective relationship with what
the world is throwing at me now
but by effective relationship what i
mean is that what i do
how i how i actually show up increases
my possibility of being in an effective
relationship with what the world is
throwing at me in the future
that's it okay i'm gonna push back a
little bit
one could argue that in the current
world that would say to be meaningful is
to become a
very good game a player well
if game a was in fact a really
valid future then that would be true
and it was at some point so there was a
time that being meaningful
was figuring out what are the
affordances of game a and getting damn
good at it
for a period of time that was very true
and this is actually quite challenging
because
remember i said this is i think this is
actually a very interesting piece
when i said the game b is sort of
omnipresent but we may be playing it at
level zero
i mean that quite seriously i mean that
like 35 000 years ago
game b was present but gay man game b
are co-present and so there's this
really interesting tension that we can
feel in ourselves that
as we sort of follow the meaningfulness
vector in the direction of game a
we can notice a a tension or a lack of
integrity a fragmentation of ourself
in relationship to the meaningful
inspector in the direction of game b
because there's a discontinuity between
the two
and i think that is is really really a
deep
point like it speaks to why we may have
a subjective sense of
the [ __ ] is rut talking about or what is
paul talking about when he says that
to play game a well was meaningfulness
in say the 1950s or say the 1300s
and that's because in in the in the
larger scheme of things right we've been
doing this this human thing for a
million years and so the 35 000 years
where game a was a certain
had a certain conformity to it it's just
a blink of the eye so
we might say is that our deep deep deep
sense of meaningfulness
has kind of always felt that game a has
this
this taste of short-termism a taste of
making trade-offs between things and
maybe they are the right trade-offs
maybe i have to make those trade-offs
i want to continue to be able to play
the game but i also feel a certain
wrongness to it
and so one of the things we might say is
that the fulfillment of game b
is a recovery of that and moving back
into an alignment that the
even our evolutionary selves can feel is
ah
now i no longer have to in order to
pursue this path of what is actually
meaningful
i can actually pursue a path that is
feeling increasingly meaningful
all the way down and all the way out
which is a very nice orientation
essentially you talk about the sense of
wrongness
that keeps popping up and i'm going to
give two good examples
that were actually pretty major and had
some result in game a and
and twice challenged game a one
is marx's idea of alienation you know
the idea that
the ever crunching machinery of
capitalism while it delivers the
productive goods at least for
many people alienates people from a
holistic approach
to life and work and he predicted would
eventually
uh realize uh that they were alienated
and revolt and
in reality it turned out game a was good
enough at buying them out off
from their alienation that uh they have
been
so far willing to remain alienated the
second
i think closely related concept again a
sense of wrongness
was from the uh 60s call it the hippie
movement or whatever
whatever it was was going on in the 60s
the word there was
inauthenticity that people were walking
away from and
you know a lot of people about my age
especially one just a little teeny bit
older got decent college educations and
walked away and you know built hippy
communes so to speak to try to
achieve more authenticity in their life
you know the feeling that you know
putting on the gray flannel suit and
going to work in the big bureaucratic
uh behemoths was not an authentic way
of honoring our being as creatures in
the world
yeah those both sort of i think get it
your sense
absolutely and we can say that you know
one of the words that i think rings very
nicely
now in this context of meaningfulness as
we've described it is integrity
and here integrity has a lot of like
landscaping quite nicely we think about
it like
structural integrity which is to say
that
all of the pieces are fitting together
well
so alienation is fragmentation where
okay i've got some pieces that are
fitting together while there's a whole
other bunch of pieces that are not
and that's what alienation is right and
inauthenticity is kind of the same thing
and so in this perspective we can look
at it from a
meta level like oh wow so the
orientation towards meaningfulness
includes within itself an awareness of
all the different pieces of myself
and in fact by the way of the whole
world that are
not in integrity they are not in right
relationship with each other and by the
way
therefore have less structural integrity
so
as we begin to be aware of this we're
like okay yeah those guys were picking
things up and by the way
we can run back in time and see this
happening all the time like constantly
we were noticing
that the trade-offs that we were forced
to make by the reality of the world that
we were in
and you know that's just been the
reality whether it was the trade-off of
which of your children dies because you
haven't got enough food or the reality
of you're going to kill that other
sentient human being because you're at
war whatever it is
is a separation from a larger integrity
a larger
movement of meaningfulness that is
subject to the contingencies of now
but we feel in ourselves a wrongness to
it and
it's like a pragmatic acceptance now of
saying okay
we're going to be very aware of how do
we move more and more in that direction
of a greater and greater rightness
non-utopian right i'm not ex proposing
by any stretch of the imagination either
that we're going to be able to teleport
from here
to there we have to actually grow our
capacity to include more and more
of ourselves and the world in this
meaningfulness
and also non-utopian in the sense of
there is no endpoint where there's just
an ongoingness of an increasing capacity
to include more and more of ourselves
and other people and the world in
something that has
deeper and stronger and richer integrity
all right that's 11 minutes not bad for
jim and
jordan trying to talk about
meaningfulness